So I wanted to tell a story
أود أن أخبركم بقصة
that really obsessed me when I was writing my new book,
والتي تملكتني أثناء تأليف كتابي
and it's a story of something that happened
إنها قصة عن شيء حدث،
3,000 years ago,
منذ 3.000 سنة،
when the Kingdom of Israel was in its infancy.
عندما كانت مملكة إسرائيل في بدايتها.
And it takes place in an area called the Shephelah
وحدثت القصة في منطقة تسمى شفيللا
in what is now Israel.
موجودة في إسرائيل حاليّا.
And the reason the story obsessed me is that
والسبب الذي جعلني مهووسا بتلك القصة هو
I thought I understood it, and then I went back over it
أنّني اعتقدت أنّني فهمتها، ثم عندما راجعتها مرة أخرى
and I realized that I didn't understand it at all.
أدركت أنني لم أفهمها على الإطلاق.
Ancient Palestine had a -- along its eastern border,
كان لفلسطين القديمة -- على طول حدها الشرقي,
there's a mountain range.
كانت هناك سلسلة جبلية،
Still same is true of Israel today.
والتي لا تزال موجودة حتى الآن.
And in the mountain range are all of the ancient cities
وفي ذلك النطاق كانت تقبع كل المدن القديمة للإقليم
of that region, so Jerusalem, Bethlehem, Hebron.
القدس، بيت لحم و الخليل.
And then there's a coastal plain
ثم هناك السهل الساحلي
along the Mediterranean, where Tel Aviv is now.
على البحر الأبيض المتوسط، حيث توجد تل أبيب الآن.
And connecting the mountain range with the coastal plain
وتربط بين النطاق الجبلي والسهل الساحلي
is an area called the Shephelah,
منطقة سميت شفيللا، وهي
which is a series of valleys and ridges that run east to west,
عبارة عن مجموعة من الوديان والأخاديد تمتد من الشرق إلى الغرب،
and you can follow the Shephelah, go through the Shephelah
وشفيللا كانت السبيل
to get from the coastal plain to the mountains.
لتمضي إلى الجبال من السهل الساحلي.
And the Shephelah, if you've been to Israel, you'll know
ولو أنّك ذهبت لإسرائيل، فستعرف أن شفيللا
it's just about the most beautiful part of Israel.
هى من أجمل المناطق هناك.
It's gorgeous, with forests of oak
إنها خلابة، بأحراش البلوط
and wheat fields and vineyards.
وحقول القمح وتكعيبات العنب.
But more importantly, though, in the history of that region,
ولكن الأكثر أهمية في تاريخ ذلك الإقليم،
it's served, it's had a real strategic function,
هو كونه يمتلك ميزة إستراتيجية،
and that is, it is the means by which hostile armies
بمعنى أنه كان الوسيلة للجيوش المعادية
on the coastal plain find their way,
الآتية من السهل الساحلي للمرور،
get up into the mountains and threaten those living in the mountains.
ليعتلوا الجبال و يهددوا من يعيشون فيها.
And 3,000 years ago, that's exactly what happens.
ومنذ 3.000 سنة، هذا ما حدث بالضبط.
The Philistines, who are the biggest of enemies
الفلسطينيون القدماء، وهم أخطر الأعداء
of the Kingdom of Israel,
لمملكة إسرائيل،
are living in the coastal plain.
كانوا يعيشون في السهل الساحلي.
They're originally from Crete. They're a seafaring people.
جزيرة كريت هى موطنهم الأصلي. ويعملون بالبحر.
And they may start to make their way
ومن الممكن أن يجدوا طريقا لهم
through one of the valleys of the Shephelah
يصل بهم إلى وديان شفيللا
up into the mountains,
إلى أعالى الجبال،
because what they want to do is occupy the highland area
لأن مرادهم كان احتلال المنطقة العالية
right by Bethlehem and split the Kingdom of Israel in two.
بالقرب من بيت لحم، وبذلك يقسمون المملكة إلى نصفين.
And the Kingdom of Israel, which is headed by King Saul,
ومملكة إسرائيل والتي كان يحكمها الملك شأوول،
obviously catches wind of this,
من الواضح أنها تفطّنت لذلك،
and Saul brings his army down from the mountains
فقام شأوول بإنزال الجيش من الجبال للسفح
and he confronts the Philistines in the Valley of Elah,
و واجه الفلسطينيين القدماء في وادي إيلاه،
one of the most beautiful of the valleys of the Shephelah.
وهو من أجمل وديان شفيللا.
And the Israelites dig in along the northern ridge,
عسكر العبرانيون على طول الأخدود الشمالي،
and the Philistines dig in along the southern ridge,
بينما عسكر الفلسطينييون على طول الإخدود الجنوبي,
and the two armies just sit there for weeks
ومكث الجيشان هكذا لمدة اسبوعين
and stare at each other, because they're deadlocked.
يحدّقان ببعضهما، لأنهما في طريق مسدود.
Neither can attack the other, because to attack the other side
لا يستطيع أي منهما أن يهاجم الآخر، لأنّ مهاجمة الجانب الآخر
you've got to come down the mountain into the valley
يتطلّب الابتعاد عن الجبال إلى الوادي
and then up the other side, and you're completely exposed.
و يصبح بذلك مكشوفا تماما من الجانب الآخر.
So finally, to break the deadlock,
أخيرا و لحلّ هذه الورطة،
the Philistines send their mightiest warrior
أرسل الفلسطينييون محاربهم الأعظم
down into the valley floor, and he calls out
لباحة الوادي، و قد نادا
and he says to the Israelites,
مخاطبا العبرانيين،
"Send your mightiest warrior down,
"أرسلوا لي بأقوى محاربيكم،
and we'll have this out, just the two of us."
وسنحسم الأمر فيما بيننا."
This was a tradition in ancient warfare called single combat.
كان ذلك تقليدا في الحروب القديمة يسمى بالتلاحم الفردي.
It was a way of settling disputes
كانت معركة بين اثنين لفض النزاعات
without incurring the bloodshed of a major battle.
بدون تكبد إراقة الدماء لمعركة كبرى
And the Philistine who is sent down,
والفلسطيني الذي أرسل،
their mighty warrior, is a giant.
محاربهم الأعظم، كان عملاقا.
He's 6 foot 9.
يضاهي المترين طولا.
He's outfitted head to toe in this glittering bronze armor,
يغطيه رداؤه البرونزي اللامع من رأسه لأخمص قدميه،
and he's got a sword and he's got a javelin
لديه سيف ورمح
and he's got his spear. He is absolutely terrifying.
ومعه حربته. كان في هيئة مرعبة تماما.
And he's so terrifying that none of the Israelite soldiers want to fight him.
مرعبا لدرجة أنّ ما من أحد من الإسرائيليين تجرّأ على قتاله.
It's a death wish, right? There's no way they think they can take him.
أن يقاتله أحد يعني أنه سيموت لا محالة، أليس كذلك؟ لا توجد طريقة في إعتقادهم يستطيعون بها القضاء عليه.
And finally the only person who will come forward
وأخيرا الشخص الوحيد الذي سيتقدّم
is this young shepherd boy,
هو ذلك الراعي الصغير،
and he goes up to Saul and he says, "I'll fight him."
يذهب للملك شأوول ويقول له:"أنا سأقاتله."
And Saul says, "You can't fight him. That's ridiculous.
يرد عليه شأوول "لا يمكنك أن تقاتله، هذا سخف.
You're this kid. This is this mighty warrior."
أنت طفل وهو المحارب الأعظم."
But the shepherd is adamant. He says, "No, no, no,
الراعي كان معاندا. قال, " لا لا لا،
you don't understand, I have been defending my flock
أنت لا تفهم، لقد كنت أدافع عن قطيعي
against lions and wolves for years. I think I can do it."
ضدّ الأسود والذئاب لسنوات. أعتقد أنني أستطيع أن أقضي عليه."
And Saul has no choice. He's got no one else who's come forward.
ولم يكن لـشأوول أىّ خيار. فلم يكن لديه مستقدم آخر يدفع به.
So he says, "All right."
لذلك قال "حسنا."
And then he turns to the kid, and he says,
ثم التفت إلى الصبي وقال،
"But you've got to wear this armor. You can't go as you are."
"ولكنك يجب أت ترتدي هذا الدرع. لا يمكنك أن تمضي إليه كما أنت."
So he tries to give the shepherd his armor,
بينما يهمّ بإعطاء درعه للراعي،
and the shepherd says, "No."
قال الراعي: "لا."
He says, "I can't wear this stuff."
قال: "لا يمكنني ارتداء هذه الأشياء."
The Biblical verse is, "I cannot wear this for I have not proved it,"
الآية في الإنجيل تقول: "لا أستطيع أن آخذها، فلم أثبت منها"
meaning, "I've never worn armor before. You've got to be crazy."
بمعنى: "أنا لم أرتدي درعا في حياتي، لابد أنك مجنون."
So he reaches down instead on the ground
و بدلا من ذلك ينظر إلى الأرض
and picks up five stones
و يلتقط خمسة أحجار
and puts them in his shepherd's bag
و يضعهم في حقيبته
and starts to walk down the mountainside to meet the giant.
ويبدأ في النزول من على جانب الجبل ليقابل العملاق.
And the giant sees this figure approaching,
ويرى العملاق هذا الطفل مقتربا منه،
and calls out, "Come to me so I can feed your flesh
فينادي, "فلتأتي إلىَ لأطعم لحمك
to the birds of the heavens and the beasts of the field."
لطيور السماء و ضباع الحقول."
He issues this kind of taunt towards this person
يشير إليه بهذه الإشارة المستهزئة
coming to fight him.
وهو قادم لقتاله.
And the shepherd draws closer and closer,
ويقترب الراعي منه أكثر فأكثر،
and the giant sees that he's carrying a staff.
ويرى العملاق أنه يحمل شيئا.
That's all he's carrying.
و هو كلّ ما يحمله.
Instead of a weapon, just this shepherd's staff,
بدلا من السلاح، مجرد متعلقات لراع،
and he says -- he's insulted --
يقول -- شاعرا بالإهانة --
"Am I a dog that you would come to me with sticks?"
"هل أنا كلب لتأتي إليّ ببعض العصى؟"
And the shepherd boy takes one of his stones
و يتناول الراعي حجرا من حجارته
out of his pocket, puts it in his sling
ويضعها في مقلاعه
and rolls it around and lets it fly
ويلفها ويتركها لتنطلق
and it hits the giant right between the eyes --
لتضرب العملاق بين عينيه تماما --
right here, in his most vulnerable spot --
هنا، في أكثر الأجزاء ضعفا --
and he falls down either dead or unconscious,
و يتهاوى العملاق إما ميتا أو فاقدا للوعي،
and the shepherd boy runs up and takes his sword
ويجري الراعي ملتقطا لسيفه
and cuts off his head,
ويفصل به رأس العملاق عن جسده،
and the Philistines see this and they turn and they just run.
ويرى الفلسطينيون هذا المشهد فيستديرون لا يفكّرون إلا بالفرار.
And of course, the name of the giant is Goliath
وبالطبع، جالوت كان اسم العملاق
and the name of the shepherd boy is David,
وكان داوود الراعي الصبي،
and the reason that story has obsessed me
و السبب في هوسي بتلك القصة
over the course of writing my book
طوال فترة تأليفي لكتابي
is that everything I thought I knew about that story
هو أنّ كل شيء حسبت أنني أعرفه عن تلك القصة
turned out to be wrong.
اكتشفت أنّه خطأ.
So David, in that story, is supposed to be the underdog, right?
فداوود في تلك القصة، كان يفترض أن يكون المستضعف، أليس كذلك؟
In fact, that term, David and Goliath,
في الواقع، هذا المصطلح، داوود واجلوت،
has entered our language as a metaphor for
دخل في لغتنا -الإنجليزية- كمجاز
improbable victories
لانتصارات بعيدة الإحتمال
by some weak party over someone far stronger.
من قبل فرقة ضعيفة على أخرى تفوقها قوّة بكثير.
Now why do we call David an underdog?
الآن لماذا نعتبر داوود مستضعفا؟
Well, we call him an underdog because he's a kid,
حسنا، نطلق عليه هذا الإسم لأنّه طفل،
a little kid, and Goliath is this big, strong giant.
صبي صغير، وجالوت رجل ضخم في منتهى القوة.
We also call him an underdog
والذي نعتبره مظلوما أيضا
because Goliath is an experienced warrior,
لأنه كان محاربا متمرسا،
and David is just a shepherd.
وداوود كان مجرد راعِ.
But most importantly, we call him an underdog
ولكن الأكثر أهمية، نطلق عليه هذا الإسم
because all he has is -- it's that Goliath is outfitted with
لأن كل ما يمتلكه -- كان جالوت مزوّدا بذلك العتاد
all of this modern weaponry,
بكل تلك الأسلحة الحديثة،
this glittering coat of armor
درع لامع يغطي جسده بالكامل
and a sword and a javelin and a spear,
وسيف ورمح وحربة،
and all David has is this sling.
وكل ما كان لدى الصبي هو مجرد مقلاع.
Well, let's start there with the phrase
حسنا, دعونا نبدأ بعبارة
"All David has is this sling,"
"داوود ليس له سوى مقلاعه"،
because that's the first mistake that we make.
لأنّ هذا هو أول خطأ نقوم به.
In ancient warfare, there are three kinds of warriors.
في الحروب القديمة، هناك ثلاث أنواع من المحاربين.
There's cavalry, men on horseback and with chariots.
الفارس، على ظهر حصان وعربة حربية.
There's heavy infantry, which are foot soldiers,
هناك المشاة، وهم الجنود الذين يمشون على أقدامهم،
armed foot soldiers with swords and shields
مزوّدين بسيوف و أوقية
and some kind of armor.
و بعض أنواع الدروع.
And there's artillery, and artillery are archers,
وهناك المدفعية، وأقصد بهم رماة الأسهم،
but, more importantly, slingers.
لكن الأكثر أهمية هم الحباليين.
And a slinger is someone who has a leather pouch
والحبّال هو شخص لديه كيس من الجلد
with two long cords attached to it,
بحبلين طويلين ملحقان به،
and they put a projectile, either a rock or a lead ball,
ويضعون مقذوفا، صخرة أو كرة معدنية،
inside the pouch, and they whirl it around like this
في الكيس، و يديرونه هكذا
and they let one of the cords go,
ويفلتون حبلا من الحبلين،
and the effect is to send the projectile forward
فينطلق المقذوف للأمام
towards its target.
تجاه الهدف
That's what David has, and it's important to understand
هذا ما كان لدى داوود، ومن المهم أن نفهم
that that sling is not a slingshot.
أنّ السرج ليس مقلاعا.
It's not this, right? It's not a child's toy.
أليس كذلك؟ إنّه ليس لعبة أطفال.
It's in fact an incredibly devastating weapon.
إنه في الواقع سلاح في غاية التدمير.
When David rolls it around like this,
عندما يديره داوود هكذا،
he's turning the sling around probably
يدير السرج حوله بشكل مناسب
at six or seven revolutions per second,
بسرعة ست أو سبع عدات في الثانية،
and that means that when the rock is released,
وهذا معناه أنّه عندما تنطلق الصخرة،
it's going forward really fast,
فستنطلق للأمام بسرعة هائلة،
probably 35 meters per second.
من المحتمل أن تنطلق بسرعة 35 مترا في الثانية.
That's substantially faster than a baseball
وهذا أسرع من طابة كرة القاعدة بشكل ملحوظ،
thrown by even the finest of baseball pitchers.
مضروبة من أمهر لاعبي كرة القاعدة.
More than that, the stones in the Valley of Elah
والأكثر من ذلك أنّ الأحجار في وادي إيلاه
were not normal rocks. They were barium sulphate,
لم تكن أحجارأ عادية. إنها أحجار كبريتات الباريوم،
which are rocks twice the density of normal stones.
والتي تضاعف كثافتها كثافة الأحجار العادية.
If you do the calculations on the ballistics,
لو نقوم بحساب ذلك بقوانين القذائف،
on the stopping power of the rock fired from David's sling,
في وقت ارتطام الصخرة المقذوفة بواسطة سرج داوود،
it's roughly equal to the stopping power
ستكون تقريبا معادلة لقوة ارتطام
of a [.45 caliber] handgun.
رصاصة من مسدس [عيار 45,].
This is an incredibly devastating weapon.
هذا سلاح غاية في التدمير.
Accuracy, we know from historical records
على وجه الدقة، نحن نعرف من الوثائق التاريخية
that slingers -- experienced slingers could hit
أن الحبّالين -- الحبّالين المتمرسين بإمكانهم إصابة
and maim or even kill a target at distances of up to 200 yards.
وتعجيز أو حتى قتل هدف من على مسافة 200 قدم.
From medieval tapestries, we know that slingers
من الأبسطة المزخرفة من حقبة العصور الوسطى، نعلم أن الحبّالين
were capable of hitting birds in flight.
كان في إمكانهم إصابة الطيور أثناء الطيران.
They were incredibly accurate.
كانت في منتهى الدقة بشكل هائل.
When David lines up -- and he's not 200 yards away from Goliath,
عندما اصطف داوود -- وهو ليس على بعد 200 قدم من جالوت،
he's quite close to Goliath --
إنه قريب تماما من جالوت --
when he lines up and fires that thing at Goliath,
عندما اصطف مواجها جالوت مطلقا عليه تلك المقذوفة،
he has every intention and every expectation
كانت لديه النية الواضحة والتوقع اليقيني
of being able to hit Goliath at his most vulnerable spot
أن بإمكانه إصابة جالوت في مقتل
between his eyes.
بين عينيه.
If you go back over the history of ancient warfare,
لو راجعت تاريخ الحروب القديمة،
you will find time and time again
ستجد ذلك مرارا وتكرارا
that slingers were the decisive factor against infantry
أنّ الحبالين كانوا الأكثر حسما في المعارك بالمقارنة بالمشاة
in one kind of battle or another.
في نوع أو آخر من المعارك.
So what's Goliath? He's heavy infantry,
فأي نوع من المحاربين كان جالوت؟ كان من المشاة،
and his expectation when he challenges the Israelites to a duel
وكان توقعه عندما تحدى العبرانيون أن ينازله أحدهم
is that he's going to be fighting another heavy infantryman.
أنه سينازل احد الجنود المشاة مثله.
When he says, "Come to me that I might
عندما قال للراعي، "فلتأتي إلي لأطعم
feed your flesh to the birds of the heavens and the beasts of the field,"
لحمك لطيور السماء وضباع الحقول"
the key phrase is "Come to me."
الكلمة الرئيسية هنا "فلتأتي إليَ."
Come up to me because we're going to fight,
تعالى إليّ لأنّنا سنتقاتل،
hand to hand, like this.
يدا بيد، هكذا.
Saul has the same expectation.
شأوول كان لديه نفس التّوقع.
David says, "I want to fight Goliath,"
داوود قال: "أريد منازلة جالوت"
and Saul tries to give him his armor,
وشأوول يحاول أن يعطيه درعه،
because Saul is thinking, "Oh, when you say 'fight Goliath,'
لأنّ شأوول كان يقول لنفسه. "عندما تقول 'منازلة جالوت'،
you mean 'fight him in hand-to-hand combat,'
فإنّك تعني 'أن تلتحم معه في معركة,'
infantry on infantry."
جندي مشاه مقابل آخر مثله."
But David has absolutely no expectation.
ولكن داوود لم يكن لديه أدنى نية
He's not going to fight him that way. Why would he?
في أن ينازله بتلك الطريقة. ولماذا كان سيفكر هكذا؟
He's a shepherd. He's spent his entire career
إنه راع. أمضى عمره كراعي
using a sling to defend his flock against lions and wolves.
مستعملا سرجه في صد هجمات الأسود والذئاب عن قطيعه.
That's where his strength lies.
وهذا موطن قوته.
So here he is, this shepherd, experienced
فها هو ذا، ذلك الراعي، المتمرس
in the use of a devastating weapon,
في استعمال سلاح مدمر،
up against this lumbering giant
في مواجهة ذلك العملاق الضخم
weighed down by a hundred pounds of armor
برداء مصفح يزن حولي مائة رطل
and these incredibly heavy weapons
بالإضافة لتلك الأسلحة الأخرى الغاية في الثقل
that are useful only in short-range combat.
والتي تجدي نفعا فقط في تلاحم داخل نطاق قصير.
Goliath is a sitting duck. He doesn't have a chance.
جالوت كان كالبطة الجالسة. لم يكن لديه فرصة للنّجاة.
So why do we keep calling David an underdog,
فلماذا نستمر في تسمية داوود بالمستضعف
and why do we keep referring to his victory as improbable?
ولماذا نشير إلى نصره بأنه كان احتمالا بعيدا؟
There's a second piece of this that's important.
هناك جزء آخر مهم في هذه القصة.
It's not just that we misunderstand David
ليس فقط أننا أسأنا فهم داوود
and his choice of weaponry.
وكيفية اختيار سلاحه.
It's also that we profoundly misunderstand Goliath.
بل هو أننا أسئنا فهم جالوت للغاية.
Goliath is not what he seems to be.
جالوت ليس كما يبدو عليه.
There's all kinds of hints of this in the Biblical text,
هناك كل أنواع الإشارات في النص الإنجيلي،
things that are in retrospect quite puzzling
أشياء محيرة تسرد بطريقة ارتجاعية
and don't square with his image as this mighty warrior.
ولا تتماشى مع تصورنا لذلك المحارب بأنه المحارب الأعظم.
So to begin with, the Bible says that Goliath
فبدءا، يقول النص أن جالوت
is led onto the valley floor by an attendant.
أُقتيد لباحة الوادي بواحد ممن شهدوا المعركة.
Now that is weird, right?
الآن يبدو الأمر غريبا، أليس كذلك؟
Here is this mighty warrior
ها هو ذا المحارب الأعظم
challenging the Israelites to one-on-one combat.
متحديا العبرانيين لمعركة رجل لرجل.
Why is he being led by the hand
فلماذا يقوده أحدهم من يده
by some young boy, presumably,
من قبل صبي صغير على الأرجح،
to the point of combat?
لنقطة التلاحم؟
Secondly, the Bible story makes special note
ثانيا، القصة الإنجيلية تعطي ملحوظة أخرى خاصة
of how slowly Goliath moves,
عن تحرك جالوت البطيء،
another odd thing to say when you're describing
وهو شيء آخر غريب ليُذكر عندما تصف
the mightiest warrior known to man at that point.
المحارب الأعظم لمن في عصره.
And then there's this whole weird thing
وبعد ذلك هناك ذلك الشيء الغريب جدا
about how long it takes Goliath to react
وهو عن الوقت الذي قضاه جالوت ليقوم بردة فعل
to the sight of David.
لرؤيته لداوود.
So David's coming down the mountain,
الصورة هكذا، داوود هابطا من الجبل،
and he's clearly not preparing for hand-to-hand combat.
ومن الواضح أن جاهزيّته ليست لمعركة رجل لرجل.
There is nothing about him that says,
ليس عليه شيء يقول،
"I am about to fight you like this."
"أنا على وشك مقاتلتك على هذا النحو."
He's not even carrying a sword.
ولم يكن حتّى حاملا لسيف.
Why does Goliath not react to that?
ولم لا يكون هناك ردة فعل من جالوت لهذا الأمر؟
It's as if he's oblivious to what's going on that day.
الأمر وكأنّه غير واع بما كان يحدث في ذلك اليوم.
And then there's that strange comment he makes to David:
ثم هناك ذلك التعليق الغريب على داوود:
"Am I a dog that you should come to me with sticks?"
"هل أنا كلب لتأتي إلىَ ببعض العصي؟"
Sticks? David only has one stick.
عصى؟ داوود لم يكن لديه إلا عصىً واحدة.
Well, it turns out that there's been a great deal
حسنا، يبدو أنّه كان هناك أهتمام كبير
of speculation within the medical community over the years
للتكهن داخل المجتمع الطبي عبر السنين
about whether there is something
حول ما إذا كان هنالك
fundamentally wrong with Goliath,
علة اساسية بجالوت،
an attempt to make sense of all of those apparent anomalies.
كمحاولة لفهم كل تلك الإنحرافات الظاهرة.
There have been many articles written.
كُتبت العديد من المقالات.
The first one was in 1960 in the Indiana Medical Journal,
الأول كان في العام 1960 في جريدة إنديانا الطبية،
and it started a chain of speculation
بدأت سلسلة من التكهنات
that starts with an explanation for Goliath's height.
والتي بدأت بوصف طول جالوت.
So Goliath is head and shoulders above
فرأس وكتفىَ جالوت أعلى
all of his peers in that era,
من أقرانه في ذلك العصر،
and usually when someone is that far out of the norm,
وغالبا عندما يكون هناك شخص فوق العادة لهذه الدرجة،
there's an explanation for it.
هناك تفسير لذلك.
So the most common form of giantism
الشيء الأكثر شيوعا للعملقة
is a condition called acromegaly,
هى حالة تضخم الأطراف،
and acromegaly is caused by a benign tumor
وتضخم الأطراف يتسبب بها ورم حميد
on your pituitary gland
في غدتك النخامية
that causes an overproduction of human growth hormone.
والذي يتسبب في فرط إنتاج لهرمون النمو.
And throughout history, many of the most famous giants
وعبر التاريخ، العديد من العمالقة الأكثر شهرة
have all had acromegaly.
كان لديهم تضخم في الأطراف.
So the tallest person of all time
الرجل الأكثر طولا على الإطلاق
was a guy named Robert Wadlow
كان يدعى رابرت وادلوو
who was still growing when he died at the age of 24
والذي كان مستمرا في النمو حتى توفي عن عمر 24 عاما
and he was 8 foot 11.
وكان طوله 2.71 مترا.
He had acromegaly.
وكان لديه تضخم في أطرافه.
Do you remember the wrestler André the Giant?
هل تتذكّرون المصارع آندريه العملاق؟
Famous. He had acromegaly.
الشهير. كان لديه تضخم في أطرافه.
There's even speculation that Abraham Lincoln had acromegaly.
هناك تكهنات بأنّ حتى إبراهام لينكلن كان لديه تضخم بالأطراف.
Anyone who's unusually tall,
كل شخص كان طويلا بشكل غريب،
that's the first explanation we come up with.
يكون هذا التفسير الأول الذي يخطر ببالنا.
And acromegaly has a very distinct set of side effects
وتضخم الأطراف لديه أثارا جانبية مميزة جدا
associated with it,
مرتبطة به
principally having to do with vision.
تتعلق أساسا بالبصر.
The pituitary tumor, as it grows,
أثناء نمو الغدة النخامية،
often starts to compress the visual nerves in your brain,
غالبا ما تكبح الأعصاب البصرية داخل مخك،
with the result that people with acromegaly
و كنتيجة لمن لديهم تضخم في الأطراف
have either double vision or they are profoundly nearsighted.
إما يكون لديهم إزدواج في الرؤية أو قِصر نظر.
So when people have started to speculate
فعندما بدأ الناس في التمعن
about what might have been wrong with Goliath,
فيما قد يكون علة جالوت،
they've said, "Wait a minute,
قالوا, "فلنتمهل للحظة،
he looks and sounds an awful lot like someone
إنه يبدو من هيئته و صوته على أنه شخص لديه وبشكل دميم
who has acromegaly."
تضخم في الأطراف."
And that would also explain so much of what was strange
وهذا قد يوضح الكثير مما بدا غريبا
about his behavior that day.
من سلوكه في ذلك اليوم.
Why does he move so slowly
لماذا يتحرك ببطء
and have to be escorted down into the valley floor
و تطلب أن يُرافق لباحة الوادي
by an attendant?
من قبل أحدهم؟
Because he can't make his way on his own.
لأنه لا يستطيع أن يشق طريقه بنفسه.
Why is he so strangely oblivious to David
لماذا كان في حالة سهو عن داوود
that he doesn't understand that David's not going to fight him
و لم يتمكّن من فهم أنّه لن يقاتله
until the very last moment?
حتى آخر لحظة؟
Because he can't see him.
لأنّه لا يستطيع رؤيته.
When he says, "Come to me that I might feed your flesh
عندما قال "فلـاتي إلي لأطعم لحمك
to the birds of the heavens and the beasts of the field,"
لطيور السماء وضباع الحقول،"
the phrase "come to me" is a hint also of his vulnerability.
عبارة "فلتأتي إلي" دلالة أخرى على ضعفه.
Come to me because I can't see you.
تعالى إليّ لأنني لا أستطيع أن أراك.
And then there's, "Am I a dog that you should come to me with sticks?"
ثم هنالك، "هل أنا كلب لتأتي إلىَ ببعض العصي؟"
He sees two sticks when David has only one.
إنه يرى عصيّا في حين داوود كانت لديه واحدة فقط
So the Israelites up on the mountain ridge
فكان العبرانيون من فوق أخدود الجبل
looking down on him thought he was
ينظرون إليه على أنّه
this extraordinarily powerful foe.
ذلك الخصم ذو القوة العاتية.
What they didn't understand was that
والذي لم يفهموه هو أنّ
the very thing that was the source of his apparent strength
نفس الشيء الذي كان مصدرا لقوته الظاهرة
was also the source of his greatest weakness.
كان نفس المصدر لضعفه المضني.
And there is, I think, in that,
وهناك، أعتقد أنّ هناك
a very important lesson for all of us.
درسا هاما لنا جميعا.
Giants are not as strong and powerful as they seem.
العمالقة ليسوا بالقوة والعنفوان كما يبدون.
And sometimes the shepherd boy has a sling in his pocket.
وأحيانا الراعي الصبي يكون لديه سرج في حقيبته.
Thank you.
أشكركم.
(Applause)
(تصفيق)